<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
		<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
		-->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../information/info2html.xsl"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../../../information/info.css"?>

<!--
	StupidModel4 Displayable information about this application.
	Xholon 0.6 http://www.primordion.com/Xholon (Ken Webb)
-->
<document>
<header>
<title>Xholon - Stupid Model 4 - Cell and Bug Probes</title>
</header>
<body>

<section id="whatisit">
<title>What is it</title>
<p>This is the 4th in a series of 16 "Stupid Models". It's intended as a starting point for learning how to develop grid and agent-based models using Xholon. It can also be used to compare Xholon with other agent-based modeling tools that have also implemented the Stupid Model series.</p>
<p>This model shows how to get specific information about each bug and habitat cell. The specification states: "Make the bugs, and the cells, so they can be probed via mouse clicks on the display."</p>
</section>

<section id="xholonfeatures">
<title>Xholon features</title>
<p>In Xholon you do this by clicking on a node in the Xholon GUI rather than directly on the 2D grid. If you want to know about the bug in row 10, column 23, you should first press the Refresh node. Then look under Model --> CompositeStructureHierarchy --> stupidModel_0 --> grid_102. Then count down to row 10, select that row, and then count down to the 23rd habitatCell in that row. You can then inspect any bugs that are in the chosen or any other habitatCell. When you click on a node, information about that object is displayed at the bottom of the GUI, using that object's toString() method.</p>
</section>

<section id="creditsandreferences">
<title>Credits and references</title>
<p>Railsback, S., Lytinen, S., Grimm, V. (2005).
StupidModel and Extensions: A Template and Teaching Tool for Agent-based Modeling Platforms.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.swarm.org/wiki/Software_templates">Swarm page</a></p>
<p><a href="http://condor.depaul.edu/~slytinen/abm/StupidModel/">Author's page</a></p>
</section>

</body>
</document>
