<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">-->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../../Xholon/information/info2html.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../../../../Xholon/information/info.css"?>
<!-- Displayable information about this application. -->
<document>
<header>
<title>ECJ Tutorial 4 - Xholon App (no GP)</title>
</header>
<body>

<section id="whatisit">
<title>What is it</title>
<p>This model is a Xholon version of the Tutorial 4 application included with ECJ,
an evolutionary computation system written in Java. This version does NOT include genetic programming,
but simply uses an already-known optimal behavior. This optimal behavior is hard-coded into a
Xholon tree structure, inside the CompositeStructureHierarchy.xml configuration file.</p>
<p>This application runs for 40 processing loops. Each time step it calculates a new result value
for the function (currentX * currentX * currentY + currentX * currentY + currentY).
The values of currentX, currentY, expected result and actual result are captured each time step,
and optionally displayed in a chart. In this non-GP version of Tutorial 4, the expected and actual
results are always the same. The Xholon tree structure that corresponds to the above function is:</p>
<source>
&lt;PfAdd&gt;
  &lt;PfY/&gt;
  &lt;PfMul&gt;
    &lt;PfAdd&gt;
      &lt;PfY/&gt;
      &lt;PfMul&gt;
        &lt;PfX/&gt;
        &lt;PfY/&gt;
      &lt;/PfMul&gt;
    &lt;/PfAdd&gt;
    &lt;PfX/&gt;
  &lt;/PfMul&gt;
&lt;/PfAdd&gt;
</source>
</section>

<section id="howtouseit">
<title>How to use it</title>
<section>
<title/>
<p>Run it:</p>
<ol>
<li>Run the Java application through the XhnEalontro GUI (org.primordion.xholon.app.Xhn.java),
and select File --> Open --> ealontro --> EcjTutorial4 --> Tutorial4_1_xhn.xml.</li>
<li>Expand the Controller node in the tree.</li>
<li>Press the Start node.</li>
<li>If you have JFreeChart installed, and if you have selected "JFreeChart" as the value of the UseDataPlotter
parameter in Tutorial4_1_xhn.xml, you should see a chart that looks like the one below.
If you don't have JFreeChart installed, then change the value of UseDataPlotter to "gnuplot",
and look at the results that are saved to a .csv file in the statistics folder.
If you have gnuplot installed, it can read the .plt script in the statistics folder
to produce a displayable .png file from the .csv file.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section>
<title/>
<figure src="Tut4_NoGP_JFreeChart_1.png" alt="ECJ Tutorial 4 with no GP"></figure>
</section>
</section>

<section id="thingstonotice">
<title>Things to notice</title>
<p>Take a look at the XML configuration files in the config/ealontro/EcjTutorial4 folder.
CompositeStructureHierarchy.xml specifies initial values for the X and Y variables.
Under the GeneticProgram node, it specifies the function tree that needs to be traversed
to produce a correct result.</p>
<p>InheritanceHierarchy.xml is shared by both the GP and the NoGP versions of this application.
The primitive functions (Pf) out of which the behavior is created, are divived into two types.
A non-terminal primitive function has other functions as children (ex: PfAdd),
while a terminal function just returns its own value (ex: PfX).
Note that GeneticProgram is identified as a type of Behavior.</p>
<p>Look at XhTutorial4.java to learn how the result is obtained by traversing the tree.</p>
</section>

<section id="thingstotry">
<title>Things to try</title>
<p>Run the application, but don't press Start yet. Expand the Model node,
and keep expanding the nodes until you find multiValuedRegression_3.
This node has four children. Click on each child to see what its value of "val" is.
xVariable and yVariable have initial values of -2.0 and -3.0, while result and expectedResult
don't have any values yet. Press the Step node to run the application one step at a time.
After the first step, the values should have changed to: -1.9 -2.9 -9.0 -9.0 .
Compare the changing values with the charted results.</p>
<p>Try a different pair of initial values, by editing CompositeStructureHierarchy.xml.
Give XVariable and/or YVariable different initial values, something other than -2.0 and -3.0.</p>
</section>

<section id="extendingthemodel">
<title>Extending the model</title>
<p>This is a simple application that can be used as a starting point for any Xholon model
whose behavior is specified in a tree structure.</p>
</section>

<section id="xholonfeatures">
<title>Xholon and Ealontro features</title>
<p>Specifying behavior as a tree of functions.</p>
<p>Displaying results in a chart.</p>
</section>

<section id="creditsandreferences">
<title>Credits and references</title>
<p>Visit the ECJ website.</p>
<p><a href="http://cs.gmu.edu/~eclab/projects/ecj/">ECJ</a></p>
</section>

</body>
</document>